<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on ericlearns</title>
    <link>https://ericlearns.com/post/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on ericlearns</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2017 20:57:36 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://ericlearns.com/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>An Intro of Sorts</title>
      <link>https://ericlearns.com/post/an-intro-of-sorts/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2017 20:57:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericlearns.com/post/an-intro-of-sorts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So, I recently decided that I&amp;rsquo;d like to learn C++. Maybe not become an expert C++ developer, which I assume takes many years, but be comfortable enough
in the language to have it be useful. I think &amp;ldquo;proficient in C++&amp;rdquo; would be the right way to put it. The purpose of this blog will be for me to track my thoughts
and learning, and I also thought there might be someone else out there like me trying to learn and maybe they want to follow along&amp;hellip;or sympathize with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should say up front that I am not learning C++ as a &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; developer. I am (what I would consider) a relatively experienced Python and JavaScript (Node.js) developer.
In fact, I currently write code for a living. C++ always seemed like some monstrous beast of a language that was too difficult or not worth the tremendous effort to learn. I think I&amp;rsquo;ve
come to a point in my &lt;em&gt;programming development&lt;/em&gt; where learning C++ would help me improve as a developer, so why not give it a shot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll probably see me make reference to idioms and patterns in python &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt;. Python is currently my favorite language, but it is obviously &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; different than C++ in many ways. You will
probably also see me make egregious errors in C++, things that would make a seasoned C++ developer cry out in pain. I think this is part of the learning process, and it&amp;rsquo;s important to make mistakes while
learning new things, especially programming languages. With that being said, anything I write should NOT be used as a reference or tutorial of any sort. I mostly have no idea what I&amp;rsquo;m doing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>